<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: VMware | Radu Cotescu's professional blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/category/vmware/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-13T21:42:58+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Radu Cotescu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to install VMware Server on kernel version 2.6.38]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/vmware-server-kernel-2-6-38/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-05T12:18:56+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/vmware-server-kernel-2-6-38</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Notices:</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>VMware has declared VMware Server End Of Availability on January 2010 with the actual support ending on June 30th, 2011. More details can be read <a href="http://www.vmware.com/support/policies/lifecycle/general/index.html#policy_server">here</a>. Furthermore, VMware Server is not officially supported on Ubuntu releases greater than 8.04.</p></li>
<li><p>The VMware Server console plug-in won't work on Firefox versions older than 3.6 (I have found no viable solution for this problem).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The needed instructions for the installation can be found <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-ubuntu-fedora-opensuse/">here</a>. For comments related to the installation on machines running the 2.6.38 kernel version please post here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to install VMware Server on 2.6.35 kernels]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-kernel-2-6-35/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-01T22:37:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-kernel-2-6-35</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the tradition of my blog this is going to be another post about VMware Server on the latest kernels provided by the most popular distributions. This is actually an example of a paradox because I don't use this hypervisor any more, exactly due to the patching that has to be done. Still, there are quite a few people who like the product and it's never too late to make another good deed.</p>

<p>The (now famous) script I wrote a year ago (when Ubuntu 9.10 was released) had to be modified just a bit in order to support the 2.6.35 kernel. The change that affected the compilation of the VMware kernel modules was the change of location for two header files which were expected to be in a certain folder. Thanks to symbolic links, this is now handled without any major efforts. All the needed instructions can be found <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-ubuntu-fedora-opensuse/">here</a>. For comments related to the way VMware works on the 2.6.35 kernels please use the comment form from this post.</p>

<p>A thing to know before installing VMware Server on your machines is that VMware has declared the product End Of Availability on January 2010 with the actual support ending on June 30th, 2011. More details can be read <a href="http://www.vmware.com/support/policies/lifecycle/general/index.html#policy_server">here</a>. Furthermore, VMware Server is not officially supported on Ubuntu releases greater than 8.04.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few clarifications about VMware Server and the Linux kernels]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/vmware-server-linux-kernels/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-02T12:12:11+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/vmware-server-linux-kernels</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since Ubuntu 9.04 appeared back in April, 2009, I've started building different <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/category/vitualization/vmware/">scripts</a> that use community supplied patches in order to make the install process of VMware Server as easy as it was supposed to be. Still it seems that many of the users of my scripts misinterpret the help I offered by asking questions which have nothing to do specifically with the scripts but with how VMware Server works. To be clear in this aspect: I<em><strong> do not provide support</strong></em> for any of VMware's products.</p>

<p>When I began offering these scripts I simply tried to ease the process of installing VMware Server on various kernels shipped with the distribution I use. Considering to be a cumbersome job to manually apply patches or to start an install process, stop it in the middle, apply a patch and then continue the install, I thought that I could help by eliminating all these steps. The scripts are released with no kind of guarantee towards the success of using the product. Furthermore, it should be noted that VMware Server is not officially supported on Ubuntu > 8.04, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server  > 10.1, Mandriva Corporate Server > 4, Red Hat Enterprise Linux > 5.1 and two other less popular distributions.</p>

<p>Using VMware Server on any other distribution than the ones indicated above and in the "VMware Server User's Guide" available <a href="https://www.vmware.com/pdf/vmserver2.pdf">here</a> is solely your own responsibility. The only thing that I can guarantee to all of you using my scripts is the success of installing VMware Server on the unsupported kernels, a process which would fail without patching different files from the package. The fact that you might not be able to use all the server's features is not my problem and unfortunately you don't have an official way to obtain support.</p>

<p>A piece of advice that I might give to you is to not use VMware Server on unsupported kernels/distributions unless you are forced to. There are several other type 2 hypervisors which could do the job of providing virtual machines: QEMU, KVM, VirtualBox (which can be <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/virtualbox-virtual-servers/">daemonized</a>), etc.</p>

<p>In conclusion, if you have VMware Server related problems please <em><strong>do not ask me for support</strong></em>. If you have problems in using one of the scripts I wrote I would be more than happy to assist but that's the only thing I am able and willing to do for you.</p>

<p>Thank you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to install VMware Server on 2.6.32 kernels]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-kernel-2-6-32/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-21T00:41:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-kernel-2-6-32</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I have updated the script and the patch used for installing VMware Server on the 2.6.30 and 2.6.31 kernels to include support for the 2.6.32 release as well. Also I have modified the script so that now the VSOCK module compiles and loads perfectly into the running kernel. All the needed instructions can be found <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-ubuntu-fedora-opensuse/">here</a>. For comments related to the way VMware works on the 2.6.32 kernels please use the comment form from this post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to install VMware Server on 2.6.31 kernels]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-ubuntu-fedora-opensuse/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-19T01:20:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-ubuntu-fedora-opensuse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><strong><strong>UPDATE 3</strong>: </strong>The  script and patches have been updated to also support kernel 2.6.38. For  older kernel releases please download the archive from <a href="https://github.com/raducotescu/vmware-server-linux-2.6.3x-kernel/tree/release-1.5">here</a> (temporary fix until I will unify the solutions).</strong></p>

<p><strong>UPDATE 2</strong>: <strong>The script and patches have been updated to also support kernel 2.6.35.</strong></p>

<p><strong>UPDATE 1</strong>: <strong>The script should also work with 2.6.32 kernels from version 1.2.</strong></p>

<p>Seeing the success I have encountered with the <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-2-0-x-on-ubuntu-9-10-karmic-koala/">blog post about installing VMware Server on Ubuntu Karmic Koala</a> and helped by <a href="http://risesecurity.org/">Ramon de Carvalho Valle</a> with a better patch regarding the installation of the virtualization server on the newer kernels found in three of the most popular Linux distributions - Ubuntu, Fedora and openSUSE - I've managed to provide a script which should be able to install the server on all of these distros. Furthermore, by placing some trivial checks in a function of the script one may enlarge the applicability to a lot more distributions with common roots (Debian and all Debian-based distributions, Red Hat and all of its derivatives).</p>

<p>I have managed to test the script on both the 2.6.31-14 and 2.6.31-17 kernels which can be found in Ubuntu 9.10 and on the 2.6.31.9-174.fc12 kernel found in Fedora 12. Since I didn't have an openSUSE machine I am not sure of what is the outcome on this distribution (regarding the kernel sources; people who commented previously on my blog had no problems installing VMware Server using the previous script) but the script is made so that it automatically determines on what kind of distribution is run and according to this information it automatically installs the needed packages. Careful though, as this requires Internet access for the specific machines.</p>

<p>The good news regarding Ramon's patch is the fact that <strong>now VMware Server seems stable</strong>. No more warnings appear when compiling modules, except for <code>vsock</code>, which - miraculously - builds on Fedora.</p>

<p>Regarding the installation of VMware Server on Fedora, I have encountered some difficulties after the installation completed successfully. Basically I wasn't able to log into the web administration interface because of multiple factors. The steps which should be followed will be reminded to the Fedora users after the script completes but I'm gonna mention them here too:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>edit <code>/etc/services</code> and replace the entry located on TCP/902 port with <code>vmware-authd</code></p></li>
<li><p>disable SELinux it by editing the <code>/etc/selinux/config</code> file (permissive mode isn't enough - see comments)</p></li>
<li><p>reboot your system</p></li>
</ol>


<p>The general instructions are the same as the ones for the previous version of the script.</p>

<h3>How to</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>Download VMware Server (<a href="https://www.vmware.com/freedownload/p/download.php?product=server20">2.0.1</a> or <a href="http://www.vmware.com/download/server/getserver.html">2.0.2</a>) - gz format, <em>not</em> rpm. Whichever version you choose, keep the license key near.</p></li>
<li><p>Download my script from <a href="http://github.com/raducotescu/vmware-server-linux-2.6.3x-kernel/tarball/master">here</a> (right click, save as, extract archive).</p></li>
<li><p>Run the script with super user rights either in the same folder where you have downloaded the server archive, either by providing it the path to that folder. <strong><em>Make sure the folder where you have downloaded the server's archive doesn't contain spaces in its path name or the script will exit (giving you this reason as an error message)</em></strong>. If the script exists, it will give you a decent warning from which you should be able to tell what’s wrong. On Ubuntu at least, the VSOCK module will not work (will fail to compile), giving you a hint that your kernel sources might not be the ones for your running kernel. This is not true, as the script takes care of this before doing the hard work. Anyway, VMware Server will work without it. Example:</p>

<pre><code> chmod +x vmware-server-2.0.x-kernel-2.6.3x-install.sh
 sudo ./vmware-server-2.0.x-kernel-2.6.3x-install.sh [PATH _TO_VMWARE_ARCHIVE]
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>When you are asked about adding users to the server, if you do not provide your own account, the user used for login in the web console of the server will be <em>root</em> (maybe you <em>should</em> add yourself there).</p></li>
<li><p>Provide the license key when asked about it.</p></li>
<li><p>For the ones installing Windows guests in VMware Server, you must pick one of the following two solutions to avoid having problems with the mouse in the console:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>you run the <code>start-VMware-console.sh</code> in the terminal every time you want to launch a VMware Server console, but after you have installed the VMware plug-in for Firefox</p></li>
<li><p>you export this variable in the environment right after login such that it will be set before starting Firefox:</p>

<pre><code>  VMWARE_USE_SHIPPED_GTK=yes
</code></pre></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>If the solution worked well for you please share this info wherever you can. :D</p></li>
</ol>


<p>I am looking forward for your feedback because running the script and the server under multiple kernel versions and distributions will provide the real way to see if this latest patch really handles all the flaws in VMware Server or not. And if it does, this means that Ramon and I (but mostly Ramon) can shout a big "In your face, VMware!".</p>

<p>P.S. All my open-source work can also be found on <a href="http://github.com/raducotescu">GitHUB</a>. This is useful if you think that you have some other non up to date versions of my scripts. Anyway, the scripts which can be found on my server represent the latest version.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
