<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Virtualization | Radu Cotescu's professional blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/category/virtualization/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-28T14:25:01+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Radu Cotescu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to install VMware Server on kernel version 2.6.38]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/vmware-server-kernel-2-6-38/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-05T12:18:56+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/vmware-server-kernel-2-6-38</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Notices:</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>VMware has declared VMware Server End Of Availability on January 2010 with the actual support ending on June 30th, 2011. More details can be read <a href="http://www.vmware.com/support/policies/lifecycle/general/index.html#policy_server">here</a>. Furthermore, VMware Server is not officially supported on Ubuntu releases greater than 8.04.</p></li>
<li><p>The VMware Server console plug-in won't work on Firefox versions older than 3.6 (I have found no viable solution for this problem).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The needed instructions for the installation can be found <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-ubuntu-fedora-opensuse/">here</a>. For comments related to the installation on machines running the 2.6.38 kernel version please post here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to install VMware Server on 2.6.35 kernels]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-kernel-2-6-35/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-01T22:37:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-kernel-2-6-35</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the tradition of my blog this is going to be another post about VMware Server on the latest kernels provided by the most popular distributions. This is actually an example of a paradox because I don't use this hypervisor any more, exactly due to the patching that has to be done. Still, there are quite a few people who like the product and it's never too late to make another good deed.</p>

<p>The (now famous) script I wrote a year ago (when Ubuntu 9.10 was released) had to be modified just a bit in order to support the 2.6.35 kernel. The change that affected the compilation of the VMware kernel modules was the change of location for two header files which were expected to be in a certain folder. Thanks to symbolic links, this is now handled without any major efforts. All the needed instructions can be found <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/how-to-install-vmware-server-ubuntu-fedora-opensuse/">here</a>. For comments related to the way VMware works on the 2.6.35 kernels please use the comment form from this post.</p>

<p>A thing to know before installing VMware Server on your machines is that VMware has declared the product End Of Availability on January 2010 with the actual support ending on June 30th, 2011. More details can be read <a href="http://www.vmware.com/support/policies/lifecycle/general/index.html#policy_server">here</a>. Furthermore, VMware Server is not officially supported on Ubuntu releases greater than 8.04.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ubuntu 10.10 and VirtualBox Guest Additions]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/ubuntu-virtualbox-additions/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-12T12:00:06+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/ubuntu-virtualbox-additions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two days ago Ubuntu 10.10 was released. Since I don't want to upgrade yet to the new release - I am currently running 10.04 - I decided to try Maverick (the code name for the latest release) in a VirtualBox virtual machine.</p>

<p>The installation process went fine (it's just point and click) and I do like the new wizard's screens. Usually the next step for any virtual machine would be to install VirtualBox Guest Additions in order to be able to use higher resolutions, mouse integration, seamless integration and all the other geeky goodies. From my previous experiences, to install the Guest Additions into a virtual guest, one was supposed to click on <em>Devices » Install Guest Additions...</em> in VirtualBox's guest window and then to launch the autorun script from the virtual CD. Well, that used to work until now.</p>

<p>For Ubuntu 10.10 the process has to be slightly altered for a successful installation of the additions. This means that once you install Ubuntu in your VM you have to make sure that two other packages are installed in your guest before you use the instructions provided in the previous paragraph. The packages are <code>build-essential</code> and the linux headers for your running kernel. To install these two packages the quickest way would be to open a terminal (the GUI alternatives would be Ubuntu Software Centre and Synaptic Package Manager, but it will take you longer) and issue the following commands:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install build-essential linux-headers-`uname -r`
</code></p>

<p>Remember that <em><strong>these two packages have to be installed in your guest</strong></em>. Afterwards you proceed with the usual way of installing the additions.</p>

<p>Have fun!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few clarifications about VMware Server and the Linux kernels]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/vmware-server-linux-kernels/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-02T12:12:11+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/vmware-server-linux-kernels</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since Ubuntu 9.04 appeared back in April, 2009, I've started building different <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/category/vitualization/vmware/">scripts</a> that use community supplied patches in order to make the install process of VMware Server as easy as it was supposed to be. Still it seems that many of the users of my scripts misinterpret the help I offered by asking questions which have nothing to do specifically with the scripts but with how VMware Server works. To be clear in this aspect: I<em><strong> do not provide support</strong></em> for any of VMware's products.</p>

<p>When I began offering these scripts I simply tried to ease the process of installing VMware Server on various kernels shipped with the distribution I use. Considering to be a cumbersome job to manually apply patches or to start an install process, stop it in the middle, apply a patch and then continue the install, I thought that I could help by eliminating all these steps. The scripts are released with no kind of guarantee towards the success of using the product. Furthermore, it should be noted that VMware Server is not officially supported on Ubuntu > 8.04, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server  > 10.1, Mandriva Corporate Server > 4, Red Hat Enterprise Linux > 5.1 and two other less popular distributions.</p>

<p>Using VMware Server on any other distribution than the ones indicated above and in the "VMware Server User's Guide" available <a href="https://www.vmware.com/pdf/vmserver2.pdf">here</a> is solely your own responsibility. The only thing that I can guarantee to all of you using my scripts is the success of installing VMware Server on the unsupported kernels, a process which would fail without patching different files from the package. The fact that you might not be able to use all the server's features is not my problem and unfortunately you don't have an official way to obtain support.</p>

<p>A piece of advice that I might give to you is to not use VMware Server on unsupported kernels/distributions unless you are forced to. There are several other type 2 hypervisors which could do the job of providing virtual machines: QEMU, KVM, VirtualBox (which can be <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/virtualbox-virtual-servers/">daemonized</a>), etc.</p>

<p>In conclusion, if you have VMware Server related problems please <em><strong>do not ask me for support</strong></em>. If you have problems in using one of the scripts I wrote I would be more than happy to assist but that's the only thing I am able and willing to do for you.</p>

<p>Thank you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using VirtualBox for virtualizing servers]]></title>
    <link href="http://radu.cotescu.com/virtualbox-virtual-servers/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-27T01:07:56+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://radu.cotescu.com/virtualbox-virtual-servers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://virtualbox.org"><img src="/uploads/wpuploads/2010/05/vbox-300x225.png" alt="Oracle VirtualBox" /></a>A considerable amount of my diploma project runs on several virtual machines, due to the lack of multiple physical machines required for the job. Of course, <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/geeks-and-their-computers/">Riker</a> isn't tailored for production regarding this project, but it was built specifically to allow me to develop the code without restrictions. For a load under 10 users I think it would do the job quite okay. You might be asking yourself what kind of project it is if an Intel Core i7 930 processor couldn't handle the job. I'm not going to tell you... Yet.</p>

<p>Because of the way <a href="http://radu.cotescu.com/category/vitualization/vmware/">VMware Server</a> works on the last kernels from Ubuntu this tool couldn't have offered me the stability and performance I need. And because I really like to use my graphics card to decode HD content, Xen or VMware ESXi weren't an option either. What was left? VirtualBox is made for desktop virtualization. Still, the ease of use of this product and the fact that it never ever failed for my needs made me actually consider it could be up for the job. Of course, the only problem I had was daemonizing it somehow so that I could run the virtual machines without necessarily being logged in. It actually crossed my mind a few times to write some scripts which would rely on the CLI tools that VirtualBox provides, but the lack of time always made me think twice before this.</p>

<p>At some point in time though, I discovered <a href="http://vboxtool.sourceforge.net/">VBoxTool</a>, which coincidentally is nothing more than a collection of wrapper scripts written in BASH which help you daemonize the hypervisor. How cool is that? Provided that you set up a configuration file and add an init script to the desired runlevels (all this by following proper written explanations directly from the author), this "facade framework" (design pattern pun intended) will automatically start/resume the desired virtual machines and will shutdown/suspend them together with your host. I had to modify about four lines of code to alter a bit the behaviour for shutdown so that my VMs would always get suspended instead of turned off, but that's almost nothing.</p>

<p>The VMs that are on most of the time both run Ubuntu Server 10.04 64bit: one with 2 GB of RAM and Oracle 11G, the other with 128 MB hosting an internal repository under <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nginx">nginx</a> (which is a <em>very</em> fast web server). They both work great and my host doesn't at all feel sluggish. Actually all these three machines (host + 2 guests) run incredibly well. The maximum sustained throughput I achieved using the virtualized repository was 60 MB/s which is pretty impressive. I haven't tried yet to test the DB engine with a consistent load (a great number of queries directed to it simultaneously) but I will get that chance near the end of June when I'll perform some load testing on my application.</p>

<p>By the way, nine days ago VirtualBox 3.2 has been released (the first release of VB since Oracle acquired Sun) and a bunch of <a href="http://www.virtualbox.org/wiki/Changelog">new features</a> have seen daylight. Check it out.</p>

<p>Considering that there's a reliable way of running virtualized servers into a daemonized VirtualBox, do you still want to puzzle yourself with VMware Server's erratic behaviour?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
